בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is מ"ה, mem hey, 45,
and we pick up at the bottom of מ"ד עמוד ב'. mem
daled amud bet. We have finished going through the sort of דרשות
drashot of the פסוקים psukim about the case of כופר, kofer, and
then we moved on to a discussion about whether it matters if
there are owners of the ox. Clearly that matters for the idea
of כופר, kofer, but does it matter for the idea of stoning
the ox, since the פסוקים psukim so much talk in the context
of the owners and the ox, etc., maybe that you need to
have owners, which is Rabbi Yehuda's position, or the חכמים's Chachamim position
is that no, for the stoning itself, which the owners don't even
have to be at fault for, then it doesn't matter if the
ox is even a wild ox, you would still stone it. Okay,
so now we pick up with the משנה mishna at the bottom
and about the status now that we've decided about when you stone
the ox, when you pay כופר, kofer, we're going to deal with
the status of it as a שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, something that
we've touched on earlier as well. So the משנה mishna at the
bottom of מ"ד עמוד ב'. mem daled amud bet. שור שיוצא ליסקל,
Shor sheyotze leyisakel, a שור shor is going out to be stoned.
Interesting, right, there's a משנה mishna in סנהדרין Sanhedrin about what happens
when a person is being taken out to be executed. So here
you have the ox being taken out to be executed. והקדישו בעליו,
Vehikdisho ba'alav, and the owners say I am sanctifying it to the
בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, especially since we just learned yesterday that according
to Rabbi Yehuda if they sanctify it they prevent it from actually
being becoming a שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, but anyway whether that's true
or not, does the sanctity take hold? אינו מוקדש, Eino mukdash, it
does not take hold. At the moment that it is already being
taken out to be stoned and the גמר דין, gmar din, the
final judgment has been passed that it's a שור הנסקל, shor haniskal,
then it is considered to be איסורי הנאה, issurei hana'ah, forbidden in
benefit, and fundamentally because it's forbidden in benefit, it's seen as either
ownerless or outside the meaningful control of the owners. If you can't
get benefit from anything, you're not considered to be in control over
it, and therefore it has, and therefore you cannot sanctify it. שחטו
בשרו אסור, Shachato besaro assur, if you שחט shechted it, the meat
remains forbidden, right, even if it's not stoned. We learned earlier לא
יאכל את בשרו, lo ye'achel et besaro, even when it turns into
meat to be, it remains forbidden once there has been a גמר
דין. gmar din. So בשרו
אסור. besaro assur. אם עד שלא נגמר דינו, Im ad shelo nigmar
dino, however, if you did these things before the it was the
final judgment had been passed, even if it was in the middle
of the proceedings and it was clear that's where things were going.
הקדישו בעליו מוקדש, Hikdisho ba'alav mukdash, if the owner sanctified it, it
is sanctified to the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. Now, other than Rabbi
Yehuda, the court will still judge after it's הקדש hekdesh that it
is אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah that it is a שור הנסקל shor
haniskal and they will take it out and stone it, but at
least for the interim, it is sanctified.
ואם שחטו בשרו מותר, Ve'im shachato besaro mutar, but if you שחט
shechted it, then clearly that way you'll certainly save it from the
final judgment of the בית דין beis din because if you שחט
shecht the meat will be permissible and it cannot have a גמר
דין gmar din unless it is alive when the בית דין beis
din does its ruling. So that's actually a way where you can
subvert the system, and you will then benefit from the meat of
it, which is obviously significant if you can get your hands on
it. Presumably the court will have a will be holding onto it
and try to prevent that from happening. But if you do that,
it is not yet שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, the meat is permissible,
and what's not discussed in the משנה mishna but is the case
is that then it will never become forbidden. Then you have actually
subverted the system, yes.
So if it was judged it's like the man who's already dead
even once he's judged for?
Yeah,
it's similar to that idea. I mean we don't fully say that,
but in similar ways somebody is already judged and being taken out
to be executed then if you wound him or whatever you curse
him, all these exemption all these things that he loses a lot
of his significant status in law. Right. So here it's similar although
here it's even that's a harder idea because that's like to what
degree are we saying a person is dead while he's still alive.
Here we're just saying that he's out of the owner's control. Okay,
or he already had a status of a שור הנסקל shor haniskal
once it's גמר דין gmar din so therefore it remains forbidden even
after you שחט. shechted. But if you did these things before of
גמר דין gmar din then you have managed to subvert the system.
Now, מסרו mesaro or at least temporarily. מסרו לשומר חינם, Mesaro leshomer
chinam, now, this is now you handed this שור הנסקל shor haniskal
to before it became a שור הנסקל. shor haniskal. You gave your
ox to a somebody a bailee as the old translations would have
it, somebody whose job it is to watch the animal, a שומר,
shomer, whether he is paid whether he is unpaid, ולישואל, ulishoel, or
to a borrower who has full liability. Goes to the two extremes.
An unpaid שומר shomer who has like minimal liability, a borrower who
has full liability, ולנושא שכר ולשוכר, ulenosei sachar ulesocher, or somebody who
is being a paid watcher or somebody who is renting it, which
has a middle level liability. In all those cases נכנסו תחת הבעלים,
nichnesu tachas habaalim, they stand in the place of the owners. מועד
משלם נזק שלם ותם משלם חצי נזק. Muad meshallem nezek shalem vetam
meshallem chatzi nezek. Now now we are no longer talking about a
שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, this really should be completely a different משנה
mishna which is: what happens when you give your ox
to
somebody... which is when they are liable for damages that occur to
the object to reimburse the owner. Here the משנה mishnah introduces that
when you take an object, because you become sort of, you know,
it's sort of like what do they say like at school or
at camp that the teacher or the administration becomes what is it?
In loco parentis. So here too, even though your responsibility is to
the owner, you never became, you never took an obligation towards the
rest of the world, but if you take an object into your
care, then you do take, you become in loco בעלים, baalim, I
guess or whatever, you do become in the position of the owners
and you become responsible in terms of the damage that it does
to the larger world. Now there are ways in which you can
explicitly stipulate against that and tell the owners I'm not taking that
responsibility, but by default you are, and therefore that is what the
end of the משנה mishnah teaches, having nothing to do with the
שור הנסקל Shor Haniskal case. Now we did have a case earlier
I think about what happens if the שומר shomer can return it
to the owners, right? No, or are we getting up to that?
Actually I think we're getting up to that. No we're getting up
to that.
תם ומועד? Tam ve'muad?
Yeah yeah, so we had that in the גמרא, Gemara, but this
is the first case in the משנה. mishnah. Okay, תנו רבנן. Tanu
Rabbanan. Okay so now we're going to first look at the case
about it becoming a שור הנסקל, Shor Haniskal, about doing these things
before or after it has a גמר דין. gmar din. שור שהמית
עד לא נגמר דינו. Shor she'hemit ad lo nigmar dino. If it's
killed before the גמר דין, gmar din,
so, I'm sorry, שור שהמית, shor she'hemit, I put the comma in
the wrong place there. שור שהמית, shor she'hemit, an ox killed. עד
לא נגמר דינו, Ad lo nigmar dino, before the גמר דין, gmar
din, מכורו מכור. mechoro machur. If you sell it, it's a legitimate
sale, it's still yours, it has not become איסור הנאה. issur hana'ah.
הקדשו מוקדש, Hekdesho mukdash, if you sanctify it, it becomes holy.
שחטו בשרו מותר, Shechato besaro mutar, the meat is permissible. It does
not yet have a status even though it's in the process of
the court case. החזירו שומר לבית בעליו. Hechziro shomer l'veit be'alav. Here's
something that we did not really address in the משנה. mishnah. If
the, if a watcher, a guardian, basically you gave it to somebody
to watch before and it was a simple animal whatever it was
an ox it never did anything wrong in its life and in
I gave it to ראובן Reuven to watch and while it was
under ראובן's Reuven care it went ahead and killed someone and it
became a שור הנסקל. Shor Haniskal. Okay, then ראובן Reuven says to
me, here, here's your ox back, זאב. Zev. So anyway, so if
he does that to me, החזירו שומר לבית בעליו מוחזר. Hechziro shomer
l'veit be'alav mukhzar. If he actually gave it back to me before
the גמר דין, gmar din, okay, I gave you your ox back.
What you're complaining that it's in the middle of some court case,
yeah that's not my problem. I gave you your ox back. There's
no visible damage on your ox, end of story. Okay, משנגמר דינו,
Mishenigmar dino, yeah what's
the grandma or whatever.
I mean the court case would still go on.
Yeah, the court case would go
on.
But he did like you know, רשות משנה?
reshut meshane? Yeah, yeah, it's because that's why about מועד Muad and
תם. Tam. This is about a שור הנסקל. Shor Haniskal. משנגמר דינו,
Mishenigmar dino, after the גמר דין, gmar din, then it's already gets
a status of a שור הנסקל, Shor Haniskal, it's forbidden in benefit.
It's therefore effectively out of my control. מכורו אינו מכור, Mechoro eino
machur, if I try to sell it it's not a legitimate sale.
הקדשו אינו מוקדש, Hekdesho eino mukdash, if I sanctify it it is
not sanctified. Right, it's rather either I don't own it or I
don't have effective control over it.
שחטו בשרו אסור, Shechato besaro assur, if I שחט shecht it it
does not,
that's what we learned again from לא יאכל את בשרו. lo ye'achel
et besaro. Once there is a גמר דין, gmar din, then even
if it doesn't get stoned, even if it gets שחט, shechted, after
the גמר דין gmar din it has a status of a שור
הנסקל Shor Haniskal and the meat remains forbidden. And החזירו שומר לבית
בעליו, Hechziro shomer l'veit be'alav, if ראובן Reuven gave it back to
me, I gave it to him as a completely tame, innocent ox,
it went ahead under his control, under his watch, and gored and
killed somebody and then it was a whole גמר דין gmar din
in בית דין beis din and after the גמר דין gmar din
in בית דין beis din then he said oh by the way
דב, Dov, here's your ox back, then אינו מוחזר. eino mukhzar. I'm
sorry buddy, you have not returned my ox. This now is considered
like a different object, a damaged object that you are returning to
me and therefore you have to reimburse me. One minute, רבי יעקב
Rabbi Yaakov אומר, omer, רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov says, where are we?
אף משנגמר דינו החזירו שומר לבעליו מוחזר. Af mishenigmar dino hechziro shomer
l'va'alav mukhzar. No, even after גמר דין gmar din he can say
here's your ox back. Okay and now we're going to focus on
this debate about whether he can say here's your ox back. Yes,
מיכאל. Michael.
So my question is this, I mean how much of that is
because it already killed someone and now you're just trying to verify
or meaning let's say you gave me your ox which is in
the middle of a court case but before גמר דין, gmar din,
you know, and then I you know get it because I want
to do that. Right. Then the גמר דין gmar din happens. Then
is that considered that I gave it back to you?
Yep and that's what we're going to see.
That's like רבי יעקב, Rabbi Yaakov, according to תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma.
Yeah, yeah let's take a look. Okay let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay so it's only when all that happened
after the גמר דין, gmar din, right. Okay so okay let's take
a look. So גמרא Gemara says like this, where was I? So
what is this debate here about whether they can return it to
me after the גמר דין? gmar din? לימא בהא קמיפלגי, Leima beha
kamifligi, let's say this is the debate of the רבנן Rabbanan and
רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov whether the owner the guardian can return it
to me after the גמר דין. gmar din. דרבנן סברי אין אומרים
באיסורי הנאה הרי שלך לפניך, DeRabbanan savri ein omrim b'issurei hana'ah harey
shelcha lefanecha, ורבי יעקב סבר אומרים באיסורי הנאה הרי שלך לפניך. veRabbi
Yaakov savar omrim b'issurei hana'ah harey shelcha lefanecha.
So here's a question, right? The same way, it's very funny, you
know, you would think that if somebody becomes a שומר, shomer, they're
liable for indirect loss, right? Like if they, for example, if they
caused me a loss because of their poor job of watching, they
have to reimburse me, but it's not true. Again, it's similar to
it's, yes, but it's not indirect loss. Okay, it's similar to this
idea like we've been talking about when I cause somebody a damage,
right? It's not enough that I was indirectly responsible, it was my
negligence, it needs to operate through something concrete, through like a ממון
המזיק, mamon hamazik, right? Because it's my animal that gored then I'm
liable. But if I'm just negligent and I indirectly cause damage, not.
Now by a שומר, shomer, it doesn't need to be direct. Okay,
I am responsible to watch it, so if I'm negligent and something
happens because of my obligation to watch even if I don't I'm
not a מזיק, mazik, I'm negligent and the object got damaged, I
have to pay. But that's only when it concretely got damaged. Let's
say it there was there's no damage to the object but you're
suffering a loss as a result of my of my poor job.
So for example, the ox now is going to be stoned. Let's
say let's take the case when I return it to you before
גמר דין. gmar din. Physically the ox isn't damaged, but you're about
to suffer a significant loss because of my poor job. I'm sorry,
I'm not liable, I'm not liable just you know just for any
loss that you suffer. The the difference between a מזיק mazik and
a שומר shomer is that a שומר shomer doesn't have to do
an act of damaging. A שומר shomer it's enough that he's negligent
and damage occurred to the object but you still need there to
be concrete damage to the object. I am only liable when I
am giving you back an object that is damaged. Okay. Now therefore,
let's say the object I'm giving you back shows no physical damage
but it is worth less because it has now become איסורי הנאה.
issurei hana'ah. Okay? And the classic example would be would be חמץ
בפסח. chametz b'Pesach. You give me חמץ chametz before פסח Pesach to
watch and you're asking for it back from me and you're saying
Joe, give me back my חמץ, chametz, it's going to be פסח
Pesach tomorrow I want to at least have a you know eat
it and I'm saying yeah yeah I'll get I'll get around to
it I'll give back to you eventually. Okay and then I wait
till it's actually פסח Pesach and I return it to you. Okay
and then it's of course worthless. So can I say look, I
gave you your object back, it was an undamaged object. The fact
that I indirectly caused you a loss that you are now not
able to use it and now you're going to have to throw
it out, yeah, it's not my problem, I gave you back the
same object. Or do we say once it's אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah,
it basically is a damaged object? Okay, it doesn't have to be
physical, sometimes sort of a societal perception reality makes us see something
as worthless, as damaged. Okay, it's not just that even if there's
no physical mark. Like imagine Confederate money after the Civil War, right?
So alright, it's the same physical object, I don't know, I'm giving
it back to you, right? But do we say right now at
that stage it's actually okay now I'm sure it's worth a fortune
anyway at that stage it's actually considered to be damaged. Okay. So
do you say by איסורי הנאה, issurei hana'ah, something that's forbidden in
benefit it's considered to be damaged or not? And can I say
to you הרי שלך לפניך? harei shelcha lefanecha? So maybe that's the
debate, right? Everybody agrees you can give it back before גמר דין
gmar din because at that stage it's not yet אסור בהנאה. assur
behana'ah. After גמר דין gmar din the רבנן Rabbanan say you can't
give it back once it's אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah it's seen as
a damaged object and רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov says you can give
it back it's still physically undamaged. Let's say that's the debate. Okay.
So says let's read that again. לימא בהא קמיפלגי leima be'ha kamifligi
let's say this is the debate. דרבנן סברי אין אומרין באיסורי הנאה
הרי שלך לפניך deRabbanan savri ein omrin b'issurei hana'ah harei shelcha lefanecha
you cannot say if something is forbidden in benefit here it's yours
I'm giving it back to you it's the same object. Okay no
it's not the same object. ורבי יעקב סבר אומרים באיסורי הנאה הרי
שלך לפניך v'Rabbi Yaakov savar omrin b'issurei hana'ah harei shelcha lefanecha you
can say that. So let's say that's a very good way of
explaining the debate. So אמר רבה amar Rabbah no דכולי עלמא אומרים
באיסורי הנאה הרי שלך לפניך dekulei alma omrin b'issurei hana'ah harei shelcha
lefanecha everybody would agree that fundamentally you can say הרי שלך לפניך
harei shelcha lefanecha by איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah why? דאם כן de'im
kein or like it's sort of like דאי לאו הכי de'ei lav
hachi if you were to say that they're debating that
question נפלגו בחמץ בפסח. niflegu b'chametz b'Pesach. Okay why not debate about
a more classic case of איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah can you say
הרי שלך לפניך? harei shelcha lefanecha? Can you return חמץ chametz on
פסח Pesach and say I'm giving it back to you? And רש"י
Rashi basically says that from the משניות mishnayot and from the other
sources it seems clear that everybody agrees even the רבנן Rabbanan agree
that you can give back חמץ chametz on פסח Pesach and say
הרי שלך לפניך. harei shelcha lefanecha. That if a שומר shomer was
lazy in getting the חמץ chametz back and he gave it back
on פסח Pesach he actually is free of liability. So it seems
like everybody holds you can say הרי שלך לפניך harei shelcha lefanecha
by איסורי הנאה. issurei hana'ah. Okay if that's true responsibility
to be you have to אסור assur the חמץ chametz on פסח
Pesach yeah isn't there a לאו? lav?
Yeah whose לאו lav is it? Mine? Yeah yours the שומר shomer's
no but that's but we but we'll worry about that when we
learn פסחים Pesachim that's not our issue now. Okay but everybody agrees
that a normal איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah you can say הרי שלך
לפניך. harei shelcha lefanecha. So if that's true why do the רבנן
Rabbanan think the שור הנסקל shor haniskal is different? Okay so if
so ובהא u'beha where are we? אלא הכא בגמר דינו של שור
שלא בפניו קמיפלגי ella hacha bigmar dino shel shor shelo befanav kamifligi
the debate is whether we can finish the judgment against
the ox, not in the presence of the ox, okay? I think
I mentioned to you this other day, the ox, the ox. Okay,
the owner you need—the owner is one question and you need the
owner there, yes. Okay, but... no,
I don't think that's a good question. That's a good question, I
have to get back to you on that. Anyway, but besides the
question about the owner being present, here's a question: does the ox
also have to be present? You know, like, what is it, in
the Constitution you have a right to face your accuser? So does
the ox have the right? But he doesn't have a question of
the right; in order to have the גמר דין, gmar din, do
you need to have the ox present?
Yep, he's bringing him into the courtroom. Ah, well, you bring him
in because you need it for the גמר דין. gmar din. Okay,
so אין גומרין דינו אלא בפניו. ein gomrin dino ela befanav. ואמר
לה... v'amar leh... okay, let's take a look. אלא בהא קמיפלגי בגמר
דינו של שור שלא בפניו קמיפלגי. ela beha kamiflagi bigmar dino shel
shor shelo befanav kamiflagi. רבנן סברי rabanan savri אין גומרין דינו של
שור אלא בפניו. ein gomrin dino shel shor ela befanav. You can
only have the גמר דין gmar din in the presence of the
ox. Okay, and therefore, you the שומר shomer who allowed a גמר
דין gmar din to occur, you were to blame for the fact
that it had the גמר דין. gmar din. Why? דאמרי ליה, de'amrei
leh, the owners can say to the שומר, shomer, אי אהדרתיה ניהלי,
ei ahadrateih nihali, if you had just given me back my ox
in time, הוינא מברחנא ליה לאגמא, havena mivrachna leh l'agma, I would
have stolen it away to the swamp, remember the swamp? השתא, hashta,
now because of your negligence, not only negligence in it becoming a
שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, but your negligence in letting it the court,
letting the court get a hold of it, אפסתיה לתוראי, afasteih l'torai,
you have caused my ox to be grabbed בידא דלא יכילנא למישתעי
דינא בהדיה, beyada d'lo yachilna l'mishtei dina bahadeih, in the hands of
somebody that I cannot get it
at, you know, I can't bring to judgment, meaning the תוראי, torai,
I can't bring בית דין beis din to דין. din. But anyway,
meaning you've got my ox in the hands of somebody that it's
lost to me now. Okay, therefore, that's one—that's what they say. רבי
יעקב סבר, Rabbi Yaakov savar, Rabbi Yaakov holds, גומרין דינו של שור
שלא בפניו. gomrin dino shel shor shelo befanav. No, you actually—it wouldn't
have mattered whether בית דין beis din had taken a hold of
the ox or not, you can finish the judgment not in its
presence. דאמר ליה, de'amar leh, because then I can say back to
the owners, סוף סוף מיגמר הוי גמרי ליה לדיניה, sof sof migmar
havei gamri leh l'dineih, so in the end they would have done
a גמר דין gmar din with or without having hold of it.
So therefore, don't come crying to me. Now, the question is what
the heck does this have to do with anything? Because at the
end of the day, we're saying the question is are the owners
saying to me it's my fault that it had a גמר דין
gmar din or not, right? Okay, fine. But the question wasn't fault,
it was my fault I didn't return the חמץ בפסח, chametz b'Pesach,
but I'm still able to say הרי שלך לפניך. harei shelcha lifnecha.
It's my fault that the ox went out and killed somebody in
the first place, but I'm still able to say הרי שלך לפניך.
harei shelcha lifnecha. So who cares if it's also my fault that
בית דין beis din got a hold of it? Let me still
say הרי שלך לפניך. harei shelcha lifnecha. What difference does it make?
We weren't talking about the issue of fault; we were talking about
the issue of whether the object is considered to be damaged or
not, right?
So there's a long רש"י Rashi that tries to figure this out,
and רש"י Rashi basically says the following. If you look at רש"י,
Rashi, רש"י Rashi says...
if you look at רש"י, Rashi, it's about I don't know where
to describe it, you see where it says שמות כ"א Shemos chaf-alef
in the margins here between רש"י Rashi and the גמרא? Gemara? Yeah,
okay, so if you go up about one, two, three, four, five,
six, seven, about seven lines above that on the beginning of the
line, it says הכא. hacha. He
says אבל הכא משום הכי אמרי רבנן אינו מוחזר, aval hacha mishum
hachi amri rabanan eino muchzar, דאמר ליה אפסתיה לתוראי, de'amar leh afasteih
l'torai, etc. והזיקא דבידיים הוא. vehizeika d'veyadayim hu.
It's not indirect damage, it's direct damage. שהביאו לבית דין, shehevio l'veit
din, because רש"י Rashi says it doesn't just mean the בית דין
beis din grabbed hold of it. If the בית דין beis din
grabbed hold of it, I could say הרי שלך לפניך. harei shelcha
lifnecha. What I—רש"י Rashi reads this in the גמרא, Gemara, which is
not פשט, pshat, I actually—be—directly handed it over to the בית דין.
beis din. והאי דנקט אי אהדרתיה ניהלי, v'hai denakat ei ahadrateih nihali,
had I returned it, לאו משום דחיובא דלא אהדריה הוא. lav mishum
dechiyuva d'lo ahadreih hu. It's not that I'm liable for lack of
returning it. דאם כן בחמץ בפסח נמי לימא אי אהדרתיה ניהלי הוה
אכילנא ליה. de'im ken b'chametz b'Pesach nami leima ei ahadrateih nihali hava
achilna leh. By חמץ בפסח chametz b'Pesach say if you would have
given it back to me I would have eaten it. Okay, da
da da. So רש"י Rashi says, so therefore רש"י Rashi says the
question here is not blame and fault, that's true about חמץ בפסח
chametz b'Pesach as well and you're still פטור. patur. רש"י Rashi says
the case here is not that I let בית דין beis din
grab hold of it, but I directly gave it to בית דין.
beis din. Okay, but you could still say, who cares that I
directly gave it to בית דין? beis din? It's still the same
object. הרי שלך לפניך. harei shelcha lifnecha. So רש"י Rashi says my
ability to say I'm giving you back the same object is only
when the damage occurred by itself, indirect—not directly through my hands. But
if I directly did something to make it איסורי הנאה, issurei hana'ah,
let's take a following example, let's say...
I'm trying to think of another example... let's say I planted it,
you gave me some grapevines to watch and I planted wheat by
it and I made it into כלאים. kilayim. I directly... Directly did
something to make it איסורי הנאה. issurei hana'ah. You gave me some
flour to watch and I added water to it and I made
it חמץ, chametz, okay? But that would be different, then I came,
anyway, רש״י Rashi would say when you directly did it, you're no
longer able to say הרי שלך לפניך. harei shelcha lefanecha. Okay, now
there's a hard read of the גמרא Gemara for two reasons. Number
one is the גמרא Gemara does not say I directly handed it
over. Right, that's a special case. The גמרא Gemara sounds like I
let it be grabbed by בית דין. Beis Din. So it doesn't
say that I handed it over. Number two is, if the object
is seen as the same object, then it's the same object whether
I directly handed it to בית דין Beis Din or whether בית
דין Beis Din seized it. Who cares that I did it בידיים,
beyadayim, I did it directly? Still the object is the same physical
is the same object. If we're considering it that it's the same
object, let me hand it back. So תוספות Tosafos says differently. תוספות
Tosafos says the question is whether it is considered to be ניכר
nikar or not. היזק ניכר. hezek nikar. Remember for example, right, I
said like what is the story about, you know, about about Confederate
money after the Civil War? Okay, or let's say for example, here
let's use my כלאיים kilayim example. Let's say you gave me grapevines
and I planted or I let, it doesn't matter if I did
it בידיים, beyadayim, I let some wheat seeds grow nearby. Would you
say הרי שלך לפניך, harei shelcha lefanecha, it's the same grapevines? You're
saying it's not the same, meaning it's not just אסור בהנאה, assur
behana'ah, you can see that it's כלאיים. kilayim. You can see that
it's growing together with the wheat. Okay, you can see if you
look at Confederate money after the Civil War, you can see that
this is play money. It's the same physical money, but your lens
through which you're seeing it is you're seeing this as worthless money.
So therefore what תוספות Tosafos says is the same is true once
בית דין Beis Din has seized the שור. shor. If I say
to the owner, imagine now בית דין Beis Din has the שור
shor and I say, oh, you want your ox back? It's right
there, just go to the courtroom, you'll you can find it. Okay,
seeing it in the hands of בית דין Beis Din is seeing
it damaged. Okay, it's not like I gave them back their חמץ
chametz and you can't see the fact that it's אסור בהנאה assur
behana'ah just happens to be פסח. Pesach. Okay, you're seeing the ox
in jail there, okay, in the בית דין, Beis Din, you are
seeing a damaged ox. But here's the difference. If it wouldn't matter,
this is a little ironic, if it wouldn't matter if it's in
the hands of בית דין Beis Din or not because they could
have a גמר דין gmar din even if it wasn't in their
hands, then seeing them in possession of it is not seeing the
damage, because the damage exists whether or not they're in possession of
it or not in possession of it. You understand? Did you get
that? I mean it's more it's more making it meaning would it
be the same status if it weren't in their hands? Yes. So
therefore being in their hands doesn't make it more damaged. But since
it wouldn't be that status without being in their hands, if if
you say אין גמר דין אלא בפניו, ein gmar din ela befanav,
so it wouldn't have the status without being in their hands, then
the physical reality of being in their hands is what makes it
damaged. So for תוספות Tosafos the difference is both רש״י Rashi and
תוספות Tosafos agree the difference is not blame. You're always to blame,
but you can still say הרי שלך לפניך. harei shelcha lefanecha. For
רש״י Rashi when you do a direct act and he makes the
case that you did a direct act, you handed it to בית
דין. Beis Din. תוספות Tosafos says no, who cares about a direct
act? It's about whether it's damaged or not. The difference is, is
that do you view even though there's no physical change in the
ox, do you view it as damaged? If it doesn't matter who's
holding onto it, then you've then the damage is more abstract. But
if it matters who's holding onto it and בית דין Beis Din
is holding onto it, then the being in the possession of בית
דין Beis Din means that it is seen of as being damaged.
You had a question, Shanna?
Well that seems like a better comparison to the פסח Pesach thing
other than the how you're seeing it, because you didn't do anything
to make it פסח, Pesach, it just became פסח. Pesach.
Right, right. But you can say by פסח Pesach הרי שלך לפניך.
harei shelcha lefanecha.
Right, right, right. But I'm saying that seems like a better like
the when you were saying you can't it doesn't look different. To
me, like חמץ chametz looks different on פסח. Pesach.
Right, I was wondering the same thing. Why is חמץ chametz on
פסח Pesach any different than Confederate money after the Civil War? Right.
So that's what רש״י Rashi says.
That's what רש״י Rashi says. But then you have to read that
into the גמרא Gemara and the logic isn't as clear. Why should
the idea of doing it בידיים beyadayim make a difference if fundamentally
you're saying you see it as the it's you see it as
the same object? So רש״י Rashi whatever, now somehow when you do
it בידיים, beyadayim, you have higher liability. But רש״י Rashi has to
at least read that into the case in the גמרא. Gemara. Yes.
Well, what I'm trying to understand is you're kind of going back
and forth that oh because בית דין Beis Din can do the
גמר דין gmar din without it, but I thought we were trying
to say that he needs to be נוכח noche'ach before the... Well
we're about to see that.
We're about to see that.
That's the debate of ר׳ יעקב Rebbi Yaakov and the חכמים Chachamim
and we're about to see what that's based on.
See but I was also trying
to understand meanwhile or whatever.
Okay, so let's look at the first wide line of תוספות. Tosafos.
He says at the middle of the first wide line, ונראה
לרי דבנתפסו מאליהן נמי חייב. u'nireh le'Ri de'bitfesun me'aleihen nami chayav. רש״י
Rashi is wrong, it's not only when you handed it to בית
דין, Beis Din, even if בית דין Beis Din grabbed it. דמה
שנופל ליד בית דין חשיב היזק ניכר. d'mah she'nofel l'yad Beis Din
chashiv hezek nikar. If it once it came in the hands of
בית דין, Beis Din, it's you're always to blame, that's not the
issue, but now it's obvious that it's a
שור הנסקל. shor haniskal. דכיון דעל ידי פשיעתו נפלו ליד בית דין
חייב, de'keivan d'al yedei pshiato nafli l'yad Beis Din chayav, לא יכול
לומר הרי שלך לפניך כמו בחמץ ועבודה זרה. lo yachol lomar harei
shelcha lefanecha k'mo be'chametz v'avodah zarah. So it's not about the negligence,
it's about in the hands of בית דין, Beis Din, it is
now a visible damage. ורב יעקב לא חשיב היזק ניכר מה שנפל
ליד בית דין ומגמרס דינו. Ve-Rav Yaakov lo chashiv hezek nikar ma
she-nophel le-yad Beis Din u-migmaris dino. He says no, even in the
hands of בית דין Beis Din the damage isn't visible כיון דאפילו
לא באו לידם המגומם דינו keivan de-aphilu lo ba le-yadam ha-me-gomam dino
because they would have passed the same judgment even had it not
been in their hands ונמצא שאינו מפסיד על ידי שיבוא לידם. ve-nimtza
she-eino mafsid al yedei she-yavo le-yadam.
The fact that it's in their hands is not what caused the
damage. So seeing it in their hands is not seeing the damage.
The damage is unrelated to it being in their hands. Okay, you
can infer that it's a שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, but you're not
seeing the damage. Okay. חשיב לפי שגם אז היה נזק והיזק שאינו
ניכר. Achashiv le-phi she-gam az haya nezek ve-hezek she-eino nikar. הלכך יכול
לומר שם הא רשותך לפניך. Hilkach yachal lomar sham ha reshutcha lefanecha.
So it's like
I think it's a brilliant point. Okay, in both cases you can
infer that the שור shor is a שור הנסקל shor haniskal because
you see it in the hands of the בית דין. Beis Din.
But in one case you're inferring the damage, oh, it's in their
hands, they must have made it a שור הנסקל. shor haniskal. The
other case you're seeing the damage. The fact that they could not
make it a שור הנסקל shor haniskal without it being in their
hands means seeing it in their hands is seeing the thing that
damaged it. Okay? And therefore that makes it a היזק ניכר. hezek
nikar. That's the way תוספות Tosfos reads it. Okay, so that's the
debate of the חכמים Chachamim and רב יעקב. Rav Yaakov. And now
the גמרא Gemara turns to this debate about a שור הנסקל. shor
haniskal. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this. מאי טעמא דרבנן, Mai ta'ama de-Rabbanan, what's the reason of the
Rabbis that the ox has to be in the presence of a
בית דין? Beis Din?
השור יסקל וגם בעליו יומת. Ha-shor yisakel ve-gam be'alav yumat. It says
the ox will be stoned and the owner will be put to
death. Of course not literally, but anyway. כמיתת הבעלים כך מיתת השור.
Ke-mitas ha-be'alim kach mitas ha-shor. We treat the execution of the ox
like we would the execution of the owner, which has been very
clear from a lot of הלכות halachos in terms of what is
the type of act that makes it considered an act of murder
worthy of סקילה skila etc. But here we're taking it one step
further. מה בעלים בפניהם אף שור בפניו. Mah be'alim bifneihem aph shor
bifanav. The same way you can't pass a judgment on somebody not
in their presence, you can't pass the judgment on the ox if
the ox isn't present in בית דין. Beis Din. ורב יעקב, Ve-Rav
Yaakov, and רב יעקב Rav Yaakov would say to you no, you
gotta use a little common sense. בשלמא בעלים בני טענה נינהו. Bi-shlama
be'alim bnei ta'ana ninu. The owners can make a claim, they can
actually defend
themselves, they have to be present so that they can
challenge any evidence being brought against them. אלא שור בר טענה הוא?
Ella shor bar ta'ana hu? You think the ox is going to
make some claim in its own defense? So we're not going to
arbitrarily say the ox has to be there. Actually we rule like
the חכמים Chachamim and you cannot make it into a שור הנסקל
shor haniskal without the ox being present in בית דין.
Beis Din. Yep. Exactly. Yep. Correct. Even though רב יעקב Rav Yaakov
makes more like a common sense claim.
Exactly. Exactly. Okay.
Now we get to the next point, which is unrelated, not really
the שור הנסקל shor haniskal point, the other very important issue that
when you give it to a שומר shomer to watch, even though
your fundamental focus might be to protect it from damage, the שומר
shomer by taking it into their possession unless they stipulate against it,
becomes liable for any damage that it does to others.
Why is it in the משנה, Mishnah, this משנה? Mishnah?
Because you gotta blame the printers of the וילנא ש"ס. Vilna Shas.
Okay, in the
I haven't checked the actual משניות Mishnayos but it's quite likely a
separate משנה Mishnah in the actual משניות. Mishnayos. Okay. מסרו לשומר חינם
תנו רבנן. Masaro le-shomer chinam tano Rabbanan. Our Rabbis taught: ארבעה נכנסו
תחת הבעלים. Arba'a nichnesu tachat ha-be'alim. Four people take a step in
place of the owners. אלו הן שומר חינם והשואל נושא שכר והשוכר.
Elu hen shomer chinam ve-ha-shoel nosei sachar ve-ha-socher. Somebody who watches it
for free, an unpaid watcher, a borrower, a paid watcher, and a
renter. Okay. הרגו, Hargu, if the ox went out and gored, תם
יהרגו ופטורים מן
הכופר. tam yeiharagu u-peturim min ha-kofer. Like
anything else, if the ox is a תם, tam, then it would
be stoned but nobody would pay כופר. kofer. מועד נהרגו ומשלמים את
הכופר. Muad neheragu u-meshalmim es ha-kofer. If it's a מועד, muad, the
ox is stoned and they, the שומרים shomrim now, are the ones
who pay
כופר. kofer. גם בעליו יומת. Gam be'alav yumat. And the idea of
paying כופר kofer and who is sort of liable and has this
guilt
for loss of life, now it's not just a question of financial
liability, you also have this moral guilt here as well for the
fact that this person lost their life and you are the one
that needs to bring a כופר kofer right now. Okay.
וחייבים להחזיר דמי שור לבעליו. Ve-chayavim le-hachzir dmei shor le-ba'alav. Not only
that though, here is the קשיא kasha about הא רשותך לפניך. ha
reshutcha lefanecha. If they get the ox stoned, they have to reimburse
the owner for the fact that their ox is now stoned. Now
this is not our earlier discussion. Our earlier discussion was that they
returned it to the owner after גמר דין gmar din before it
was stoned. Then it was היזק שאינו ניכר. hezek she-eino nikar. Here
the ox has been stoned. So now they have a double liability.
They have to pay the victim's family the כופר kofer and they
have to pay the owner for getting their ox
stoned. Okay. חוץ משומר חינם. Chutz mi-shomer chinam. With the exception of
a שומר חינם. shomer chinam. He does not have to reimburse the
owner for the ox. So now we're going to figure that
out. אמרי היכי דמי, Amri heichi dami, what's the case? אי דנטרה,
I de-natra, if the ox was watched as well as it could
be, אפילו כולהו נמי ליפטרו. aphilu kulhu nami liftaru. Everybody should be
exempt from reimbursing the owner now. Here's an interesting point. Now here's
an interesting question, okay. We know that when you watch an ox,
the highest level of שמירה shmira, *shmira*, we'll see about different levels
in a minute, and it damages people, you're exempt from the damage
that it does to people or to property. What if you give
the ox, you watch the ox maximum שמירה shmira *shmira*? Are you
exempt also from if it becomes a שור הנסקל shor ha-niskal. *Shor
HaNiskal*? Are you exempt from paying כופר kofer, *kofer*? What is the
הלכה *halacha* in terms of death, in terms of the שמירה shmira,
*shmira*? Okay? So here the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*—let's figure that out as
we read the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, okay? So let's take a look.
היכי דמי heichi dami, *Heichi dami*, what's the case? אי דנטריה *Ee
denatrey*, if you watched it, אפילו כולהו נמי ליפטרו *afillu kulu nami
liftru*. Everybody should be exempt from reimbursing at least the owner, because
they did their maximum level—the level of שמירה shmira *shmira* they were
required to. And therefore, you know, they have no liability at least
to the owner, whether they're liable to other people for כופר kofer?
*kofer* is a different story, okay? So even though presumably the ox
would be stoned, they are not liable to the owner. Okay, ואי
דלא נטריה *ve-ee d'lo natrey*, if they didn't watch it, אפילו שומר
shomer חנם נמי ליחייב *afillu shomer chinam nami lechayev*. So the שומר
shomer חנם *shomer chinam* was negligent, that the ox became a שור
הנסקל shor ha-niskal, *Shor HaNiskal*, let him reimburse the owner. So אמרי
amri, *Amrei*, הכא במאי עסקינן *hacha be-mai askinan*, what are we talking
about? דנטריה שמירה פחותה shmira pechuta. ולא נטריה שמירה מעולה shmira me'ula.
*denatrey shmira p'chuta velo natrey shmira me-ula*. So we're about to see
this in the next משנה mishna *mishna*. Finally, finally, finally, we're going
to get to talking about, in the next משנה mishna, *mishna*, what
level of שמירה shemirah, *shmira* exempts me from liability, okay? And basically,
what we're going to assume here is that I need to do
the highest level of שמירה shemirah. *shmira* in order—now let me take
a step back and say this. What is a שומר shomer חנם
*shomer chinam* חייב chayav *chayav* for? And what is a שומר shomer
שכר *shomer
sachar* and a שואל *shoel* חייב chayav. *chayav* for? A שומר shomer
חנם *shomer chinam* is חייב chayav, *chayav* for only gross negligence, פשיעה
*p'shia*, okay? Which means that you did not do a minimum שמירה
shemirah *shmira*. You didn't even do the normal standard שמירה shemirah *shmira*
that a normal person would do. What's a שומר שכר *shomer sachar*
and a שואל *shoel* חייב chayav, *chayav* for? Even small negligence, okay?
Which means that even like גניבה ואבידה *gneiva va-aveida*, even if it
gets stolen—stolen is not grossly negligent, people sometimes get robbed, okay? But
even if there's just a little negligence, a שומר *shomer* or נושא
שכר nosei sachar *nosei sachar* or שואל *shoel* is חייב chayav *chayav*.
A נושא שכר nosei sachar. *nosei sachar* and a שואל *shoel* are
only exempt not when they do base שמירה shemirah, *shmira*, שמירה פחותה
shmira pechuta *shmira p'chuta*, but only when they do שמירה מעולה shmira
me'ula. *shmira me-ula*, maximum level of שמירה shemirah *shmira*. Okay? That's in
terms of their liability to the owner. Alright, so here you basically
have, you know, שמירה פחותה shmira pechuta, *shmira p'chuta*, you got this
level, okay? And then you have שמירה מעולה shmira me'ulah. *shmira me-ula*,
this level of שמירה shemirah *shmira*. Okay. If something happens even after
you've done שמירה shemirah. מעולה *shmira me-ula*, that's considered an אונס *ones*.
If something happens—what type of things can happen after שמירה פחותה shmira
pechuta, *shmira p'chuta*? That could be גניבה ואבידה *gneiva va-aveida*. I never
understood why אבידה *aveida* is considered to be not full negligence, but
we're not going to worry about that. Okay. If you didn't do
שמירה פחותה shmira pechuta, *shmira p'chuta*, then this is going to be
real פשיעה *p'shia*, gross negligence, okay? All
right. So that's sort of the level of שמירה shemirah, *shmira* and
what's considered to be the circumstances under which you are, you know,
in which what level of sort of fault of occurrence of the
sin. Now in this type of a case, okay, a שומר חנם
*shomer chinam* is חייב chayav *chayav* for this.
So a שומר חנם *shomer chinam* has to do שמירה פחותה shmira
pechuta, *shmira p'chuta*. He's חייב chayav. *chayav*—I got it—he's חייב chayav *chayav*
for only פשיעה *p'shia*. And a נושא שכר *nosei sachar* and a
שואל *shoel* is חייב chayav *chayav* for the middle level and they
have to do a שמירה shemirah מעולה *shmira me-ula*. Okay great. Now
how about the ox? What level of שמירה shemirah *shmira* do you
have to do to be exempt from somebody else—your ox—to be exempt
when your ox goes out and gores and injures somebody else? What
level do you have to do, okay? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is saying we're going to be talking about a case that you
did a שמירה פחותה shmira pechuta. *shmira p'chuta*. Okay, the ox went
out and it gored. That still is negligent enough because you only
did a שמירה פחותה shmira pechuta *shmira p'chuta* that you're still liable
to pay כופר kofer? *kofer*, you're still liable for the שור shor
*shor* because it becomes a שור הנסקל shor ha-niskal, *Shor HaNiskal*, all
of those things, because you didn't do the maximum. So you're liable
to other people, okay? But can I say to the owner: here's
your ox back? So if I was a שומר חנם *shomer chinam*,
am I liable to the owner? I'm not liable to the owner.
The fact that I did a minimum שמירה shemirah. *shmira* means that
in terms of my responsibility to the owner, I can say I
wasn't grossly negligent that your ox became a שור הנסקל *Shor HaNiskal*.
I know, it's too bad it became a שור הנסקל *Shor HaNiskal*,
people were hurt, but it wasn't my gross negligence, and therefore I
don't have to reimburse you for your stoned ox, okay? So that
would be why the שומר חנם *shomer chinam* would be exempt for
reimbursing the owner. A minimum level of שמירה shemirah *shmira* was done,
he's off the hook vis-a-vis the owner, but the other people are
not off the hook vis-a-vis the owner. That's the גמרא's Gemara *Gemara's*
answer. But now let's see how the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues to
explore that. Wait, let's just finish this. Okay, so... הכא במאי עסקינן
שנתנו שמירה פחותה shemirah pechutah ולא נתנו שמירה shemirah מעולה. שומר חינם
כלו לו שמירה. shomer chinam kalu lo shmira. So the שומר חינם
shomer chinam says, I did my job, I'm exempt to the owner,
whether the שור still somebody's still gonna pay a כופר, kofer whatever
that's a separate question, but I'm exempt from my responsibility to the
owner. הנך, hanach, the others, לא כלו להו שמירה, lo kalu lehu
shmira, and their שמירה, shmira, their job is not done. אמרי, so
now you take כמאן, keman, who are you going like? אי כרבי
מאיר i k'Rabbi Meir דאמר d'amar שוכר כשומר חינם דמי. socher k'shomer
chinam dami. So now there's a question, there's a debate, where do
you put a שוכר? socher? Is a שוכר socher in the שומר
חינם shomer chinam category or in the נושא שכר category? So רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says a שוכר socher goes down here with the
שומר חינם. shomer chinam. Okay, so our משנה mishnah said a שומר
חינם shomer chinam has gets off the hook with the owners. A
ברייתא, braita, so it's clear that our ברייתא braita is assuming that
a שוכר socher has a higher degree of responsibility than the שומר
חינם. shomer chinam. Okay, but the גמרא's Gemara just going to figure
this out. Where, where does the שוכר socher get categorized? If it
follows a רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir position that you put the שוכר
socher down here, then the שוכר socher should also be able to
be exempt to the
owners. אי כרבי מאיר דאמר שוכר כשומר חינם דמי ליתני לבר משומר
חינם והשוכר. i k'Rabbi Meir d'amar socher k'shomer chinam dami lisni levar
mishomer chinam vehasocher. Let us say that the שוכר, socher, even the
שוכר socher can say, hey, hey owners, I'm not grossly negligent, I
don't have to reimburse you for your stoned ox. ואי כרבי יהודה,
ve'i k'Rabbi Yehuda, now if it's presumably going like רבי יהודה, Rabbi
Yehuda, דאמר שוכר כנושא שכר דמי, d'amar socher kenosei sachar dami, that
says a שוכר socher is like the paid watcher, which makes sense.
So therefore the שומר חינם shomer chinam can say I'm not grossly
negligent, I'm off the hook for the owners, but they still have
to reimburse the owners.
If that's true, ליתני חוץ משומר חינם שמשומר חינם וכולם במועדים פטורים
מן הכופר. lisni chutz mishomer chinam shemishomer chinam vechulam bim'uadim peturim min
hakofer. So, let me just check רש"י. Rashi.
Right, so רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is going to say in the
next משנה, mishnah right, remember we, this has assumed that, as I
said, this is the level of responsibility to the owners. Now, when
are you responsible to, if you went ahead and you watched your
ox and it went out and it's and it's gored, okay? What
level of responsibility are you חייב chayav. if your ox gored? Remember
we discussed this before, this weird position of רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda?
So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said if your ox was a מועד,
muad, then you're off the hook by שמירה פחותה. shemirah pechutah But
if your ox is a תם, tam, you're only you need to
do a שמירה shmira מעולה. The people remember that strange position of
רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? So okay, so if we're doing רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda that puts שוכר socher in this category, which makes sense,
and we're talking about that you did a שמירה פחותה shemirah pechutah
here, okay? So then why are we having the שומר paying כופר?
kofer. If the שומר did a שמירה פחותה, shemirah pechutah
right, that's the scenario we're dealing with, that the שומר did a
שמירה פחותה, shmira p'chusah, so the שומר חינם shomer chinam can say
to the owner it's not gross negligence, I don't have to reimburse
you for your stoned ox. Then why is anybody paying the כופר?
kofer כופר kofer is by a case of a מועד muad and
you did a שמירה פחותה, shmira pechuta so everybody should be exempt
from a כופר. kofer Okay, so let's read that again. ואי כרבי
יהודה דאמר שוכר כנושא שכר דמי ליתני חוץ משומר חינם שמשומר חינם
וכולם במועדים פטורים מן הכופר. ve'i k'Rabbi Yehuda d'amar socher kenosei sachar
dami lisni chutz mishomer chinam shemishomer chinam vechulam bim'uadim peturim min hakofer.
שומר חינם shomer chinam doesn't have to pay for the stoned ox
because it was not gross negligence,
and then say also that nobody has to pay a כופר kofer.
because you did a minimum שמירה shmira. and you don't have to
pay a כופר kofer because a מועד muad is the same way
a מועד muad is you're exempt for damages that a מועד muad
does if you do שמירה פחותה, shmira pechuta. you're exempt for כופר
kofer. if you do a שמירה פחותה. shmira pechuta Okay? So the
גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב הונא בר חיננא... amar Rav Huna bar
Chinana...
I thought, I thought פטור patur is for the בעל, ba'al, for
the בעל, ba'al, not for כופר. kofer According to רש"י. Rashi.
According to רש"י, Rashi, אמאי משלמין כופר הא מסר סתמא ושמירה
פחותה.
amai
meshalamin
kofer ha masar stama ushmira pechuta. Which רש"י Rashi you talking about?
The same on the previous דף. daf. You're saying that פטור patur
is not, כופר kofer, you still might have to pay for.
No, so what you see in this גמרא Gemara is not that
way. You see in this גמרא Gemara meaning the גמרא Gemara is
imagining, right, that's why I sort of like let me get back
to that point. What this גמרא Gemara is imagining is if you
did a minimum שמירה, shmira. you would get off the hook for
the damaging, for paying for what a מועד muad did, which means
paying for damage or paying for כופר. kofer. That's this גמרא's Gemara
assumption. If the same שמירה shmira פחותה exempts you for damage that
a מועד muad does, it exempts you for כופר kofer that a
מועד muad does. But what the גמרא Gemara is also still assuming,
though, is that the ox would still be stoned, right? You see
that how the גמרא Gemara is never challenging the idea that you
stone the ox? Could be you stone the ox even if you
did a שמירה shmira. מעולה. You've got an ox that's killing people,
I don't really don't care what שמירה shmira you did, this is
not a question of liability, this is a question of getting rid
of this killing ox. Okay, so could be that you stone... What?
That's not our assumption?
It is our assumption, but we never said it explicitly. Right? We
never explicitly addressed the case. I mean, if anything you could say
it's all the more reason to stone it. I went ahead and
I put on this huge, you know, big wall, chain-link fence, whole
thing, electric fence, and it still escaped and killed somebody. Oh, well
then we won't stone it. What are you talking about? Then we...
more reason you gotta stone it, right? So presumably you stone the
ox regardless of the level of שמירה, shmira. but what we're seeing
here is that in terms of paying כופר, kofer that seems to
be exactly treated the same as whether you would pay damages, in
terms of the level of שמירה. shmira So if you did a
שמירה shmira, פחותה and you'd be exempt for damages, you're also exempt
for כופר. kofer So if the גמרא Gemara says the scenario is
you did a שמירה shmira פחותה and you can tell the owner,
I don't have to reimburse you for your stoned ox because I
did the right level of שמירה shmira if I'm a שומר חינם,
shomer chinam, then nobody would have to pay כופר kofer. if we're
dealing in a scenario of שמירה shmira פחותה according to רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda. Yes.
So I'm trying to understand is also is this תנא רבנן Tana
Rabbanan in conversation with the one in the previous גמרא Gemara as
far as כוונה? kavanah? Because the other one differentiated by כוונה, kavanah,
that
כופר kofer depends on its מועד muad status only.
Yeah, this is presuming כוונה. kavanah. Let's not get into that just
yet. Yeah, yeah, you're we're not going to get into that. But
yes, we're presuming all the normal things. We could we could complicate
it if we wanted to. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, so what's the explanation? Obviously we have to be talking about
a שמירה shmira פחותה that lets the שומר חינם shomer chinam say
the owner, I'm not responsible that it's a stoned ox, but it
still has to be that in that case כופר kofer is still
going to be paid. Okay, so how are we going to figure
that out? So the גמרא Gemara. says like this. אמר רב יהודה
בר חיננא הא מני רבי אליעזר היא דאמר אין לו שמירה אלא
סכין. Amar Rav Yehuda bar Chinana ha mani Rabbi Eliezer hi de-amar
ein lo shemirah ela sakkin. So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says the
only way you're going to you're going to watch a מועד muad
ox is by killing it, okay, which basically means that you're always
liable, you can do no שמירה shmira. to get out of it,
whether it's about damage, whether it's about כופר. kofer. Okay, once the
ox is a מועד, muad, there is no watching you can do
that gets you out of liability. Okay?
ולעניין שוכר סבר לה כרבי יהודה דאמר שוכר כשומר שכר דמי. U-le-inyan
socher savar lah ke-Rabbi Yehuda de-amar socher ke-shomer sachar dami. So yes,
we're following the רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda position of grouping שוכר socher
in here, but in terms of the liability to damage that it
causes, we will say, well, we'll figure out what liability תם tam
is, but a מועד muad you're always going to be חייב. chayav
Okay? And therefore you did this level of
שמירה, shmira you're חייב כופר chayav kofer because a מועד muad you're
always חייב, chayav. but it became a שור הנסקל. If you're a
שומר חינם shomer chinam you could say, hey, I wasn't negligent that
your ox is stoned. I don't have to reimburse. These guys, no,
they are they if this was the only level of שמירה shmira.
they did, they have still some negligence and they have to reimburse
the owners for the dead ox. Okay, so because of this, the
שומר חינם shomer chinam doesn't have to reimburse for the dead ox,
these guys do. But because it's a מועד, muad, when it's a
מועד, muad, it's always going to be a כופר kofer payment, okay,
because of
because a מועד muad never can be fully watched. Now by the
way, though, who's going to pay the כופר kofer, payment in this
case? If this is true, right, that a מועד muad always pays
even if you did whatever, right, it could be that the owners
pay the payment. Right, if we've done the watching we were supposed
to do and the animal is still liable, okay, could be that
then you gotta go back to the owner. We weren't responsible to
do a higher level of watching than we normally contracted for. Any
greater watching has to be the owner's responsibility. Okay? So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. It doesn't sound that way, right, because
it sounds like it's the שומרים shomrim who pay the כופר. kofer
I know. Okay, so anyway the גמרא Gemara, says like this. Okay.
אביי אמר לעולם כרבי מאיר וכי תניא בר אבא בר אבונה ותני
בר אבא בר אבונה Abaye amar le-olam ke-Rabbi Meir ve-chi tanya Bar
Abba bar Avuna ve-tanei Bar Abba bar Avuna reverses who said that
the שוכר socher is like a נושא שכר. Okay? He teaches
שוכר כיצד משלם רבי מאיר אומר כשומר שכר רבי יהודה אומר כשומר
חינם. Socher keitzad meshalem Rabbi Meir omer ke-shomer sachar Rabbi Yehuda omer
ke-shomer chinam. Okay? So therefore we're back here, it's a שוכר, socher,
okay, and but it would be a normal position, a רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir position. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says a מועד muad needs
a high level of שמירה and a תם tam needs a lower
level of שמירה. So this is following רבי מאיר'ס Rabbi Meir's idea
of the level of שמירה, which is a normal thing, and also
it would put רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir the שוכר socher would be
here. So you did a low level and therefore שומר חינם shomer
chinam can say I do not have to reimburse the owner if
it became a שור הנסקל, but it will be a but because
it was only a low level and this thing was a מועד,
muad, there still would be a כופר that is going to be
paid out. Okay? So that's the case of the ברייתא. braita.
Wait, I'm sorry. So if they did a lower level שמירה for
a מועד...
muad... everybody did a lower level,
then the שומר would pay.
Now the שומר חינם shomer chinam might not pay, because the שומר
חינם shomer chinam might say I understand that somebody is still paying
כופר, but it ain't me, I did the level of שמירה was
required to do. Okay, but but these guys would pay for the
כופר and they would pay for the fact that the ox became
a שור הנסקל, but not the שומר חינם. shomer chinam. All right.
Now the גמרא Gemara. says: אמר רבי אלעזר מסר שורו לשומר חינם
הזיק חייב הוזק פטור. Amar Rabbi Eleazar masar shoro le-shomer chinam hizik
chayav huzak patur. So he says if you gave your ox to
a שומר חינם, shomer chinam, if it damaged others you're חייב, if
it got damaged you're פטור. patur. Okay, so now what's the case?
Presumably you did the same level of שמירה. So if you did
a minimum שמירה you should be פטור patur in both cases, and
if you did no שמירה you should be חייב in both cases.
So היכי דמי, what's the case?
אילימא דקיבלה עליה שמירת נזקיו אפילו הוזק נמי Ilima de-kiblah aleih shemirat
nezikav afilu huzak nami If he agreed, which presumably you did by
default, agreed to accept liability for if it gets damaged, then and
you didn't do and we're assuming you didn't do any שמירה, then
you're liable even if it gets damaged. ואי דלא קביל עליה שמירת
נזקיו, v'iy d'lo kabilay shmiras nezikav, if you did not accept any
liability, which would be if it got damaged or it did damage,
so אפילו הזיק נמי ליפטר, afilu hizik nami l'ipatur, then you should
be exempt, right? It's either all or nothing. Either you accepted liability
and then you're חייב in both ways or you didn't and you're
exempt in both ways.
Okay, אמר רבא לעולם דקביל עליה שמירת נזקיו.
Amar Rava l'olam
d'kabil
alay shmiras nezikav.
Okay, no,
you accepted liability.
והכא במאי עסקינן, v'hacha b'mai askinan, what are we talking about? כגון
שהכיר בו שהוא נגחן. kegon shehikira bo shehu nagchan. You saw that
it was had a propensity to gore.
וסתמא דמילתא, v'stama d'milsa, and again, this is just what we can
presume. When you accept, I gave you my ox that was known
to be a goring ox. Doesn't matter if it's technically a תם
tam or a מועד. muad. We all know that it's that it
has this propensity to gore. And I say, Michael, could you watch
my ox, my ox with a vicious nature?
You used to say that. I knew.
You knew, right? You're presumed to have known. In a case where
it could be assumed that you knew that. And I say, can
you watch this ox? And it's presumed that you knew that it
had a vicious nature. So why do you think I'm asking you
to watch my ox if we know it has a vicious nature?
But forget that. What am I trying to prevent? Meaning, I'm trying
to prevent it from damaging someone else, right? Normally you don't have
to watch, you know, so therefore in that context, the thing that's
foremost in my mind is it might go out and damage, and
that's presumably what we've contracted. In that case, וסתמא דמילתא דלא אזיל
איהו ומזיק אחרינא קביל עליה, v'stama d'milsa d'lo azil ihu umazik achrina
kabil alay, what you're accepting liability for is that it shouldn't damage
other people. דאתי אחריני ומזקי ליה לדידי לא אסיק אדעתיה, d'asi achrina
umazkei ley l'didi lo asik ada'atey,
presumably it's not occurring to you that I'm concerned about that, okay,
and therefore you're not liable. But if nothing is said, the default
as our משנה teaches is that you're liable in both for both
things, for being damaged and damaging. But in some cases we can
presume or stipulate or presume only one of them is being accepted.
You know, it occurred to me like, why should we assume that
they both go hand in hand? And it presumed to me like,
this is what happens when you take out car insurance, right? Because
when you're taking out car insurance, they're always asking you to sign
like you want insurance for this, insurance for this, insurance for this.
Basically, you're trying of those insurance packages like the collision ones or
whatever, right? Are both for הוזק huzak and הזיק, hizik, aren't they?
Right? When you take those various insurances, right? Collision insurance is both
if the car gets damaged and if the car damages other people,
right? So it's sort of, it's understood that you're taking somebody else's
object, we gotta worry about both types of things that could happen.
Okay, so we finally now, finally, finally turn to the משנה that
we've been referring to and that I would have liked to have
been way at the beginning, which is what is your level of
שמירה required to in order to be exempt when an ox goes
and damages? Let's take a look.
קשרו בעליו במוסירה. ksharo be'alav bemosira. If the owner tied it up
with the sort of the rope, okay, it's like a, you know,
the normal sort of
reins, okay. ונעל בפניו כראוי, v'na'al b'fanav k'ra'uy, and they locked it
in the in the proper way, which is like the standard level
of שמירה. Nothing fancy here, but they did what everybody does. They
tied up the rope, they locked the gate. ויצא והזיק, v'yatza v'hizik,
and it went out and it damaged. אחד תם ואחד מועד חייב.
echad tam v'echad muad chayav. דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rebbi Meir. Rebbi
Meir says you're חייב. So for Rebbi Meir, okay, what you need
is for Rebbi Meir says that a תם tam and a מועד
muad are חייב unless you do the highest level. Okay, so Rebbi
Meir would have a תם tam and a מועד muad are חייב
even in this case. In order to be פטור, patur, it has
it has to be because you did the minimum level and you're
still going to be חייב. In order to be פטור, patur, you
would have to do a high level. That's what Rebbi Meir says.
Does that not counter to what we said before?
Before,
oh, I put the תם tam down here, but you're right, it
doesn't matter, you could put the תם tam up here. The case
was I mis-did it before but the גמרא Gemara still works. Okay,
no, Rebbi Yehuda was the one who had it inverted, right? Rebbi
Yehuda was the right I did I did split I did split
them here and I shouldn't have, okay? The case is you're both
you both need a שמירה מעולה. And our case was you did
a שמירה פחותה, the owner the the שומר was still exempt to
the owner that it became a שומר נשכר, shomer nischar, but the
animal would still be liable for still be a liability for damage
instead it did. Okay, so he says for both of them you
need a high level of שמירה.
רבי יהודה אומר, Rebbi Yehuda omer, here's the crazy Rebbi Yehuda, תם
חייב ומועד פטור. tam chayav u'muad patur. So the תם tam is
exempt so we need another color for Rebbi Yehuda.
Okay, Rebbi Yehuda says here a מועד muad you're exempt with a
low level and a תם tam you're only exempt with a high
level. So you did a minimum level, you're חייב for the תם,
tam, you're פטור patur for the מועד. muad.
Okay, תם חייב מועד פטור. tam chayav muad patur. שנאמר she'ne'emar ולא
ישמרנו בעליו v'lo yishmerenu ba'alav ושמור הוא זה. v'shamur hu zeh. When
it speaks about it going out as a מועד, muad, it says
you were warned and you didn't watch it. So in this case,
you watched it! All you have to do is a minimum level
of שמירה and you're exempt for a מועד. muad. Of course, it's
completely counterintuitive. Okay? רבי אליעזר אומר Rabi Eliezer omer אין לו שמירה
אלא סכין. ein lo shmira ella sakin. רבי אליעזר, Rabi Eliezer, we
need a third color, okay? רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer
or black, see if this works, okay? And רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer
says we don't know what רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer would say about
a, what do you call it, about a תם, tam, but רבי
אליעזר Rabi Eliezer says for a מועד, muad, you're always, you could
do the highest level and you're still going to be חייב. Okay?
All right. So let's take a look at the
גמרא. מאי טעמא דרבי מאיר? Mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Meir? What's the reasoning
of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who says that, you know, they both
need a high level? דכסבר סתם שורים לאו בחזקת שמירה קיימי. d'kasvar
stam shorim lav bechezkat shmira kaymi. I'll read this like רש"י. Rashi.
רש"י Rashi says what this means is, when the תורה Torah is
talking, we can presume, the תורה Torah is presuming that the normal
person is not bothering to watch their ox. Okay? Because, you know,
who basically normal oxen are tame and you don't need to go
ahead and watch them and prevent them from going and goring. ואמר
רחמנא תם משלם v'amar Rachmana tam meshaleim דבעי שמירה מעולה. d'ba'i shmira
meula.
And the תורה Torah says, nevertheless, okay, you're not watching your ox
and you have to pay if it's a תם, tam, which means
that the תורה Torah is trying to tell you you're paying because
you didn't do any שמירה. You had to do a higher level
than normally is done if you want to get out of paying
for a תם. tam. So you're paying because you didn't do anything.
You have to do a higher level. You have to do minimum
שמירה for a תם. tam. הדר אמר רחמנא ולא ישמרנו גבי מועד.
hadar amar Rachmana v'lo yishmerenu gabei muad. Then it tells you by
the מועד, muad, you were warned and you didn't watch it. Means
now that it became a מועד, muad, you had to do a
higher level. דבעי שמירה מעולה. d'ba'i shmira meula. You need even a
higher level. So the fact that it made you do a תם
tam means you do need to do more than zero. You need
to do minimum. Then it says by a מועד, muad, you really
were continued to be negligent, means once it became a מועד, muad,
you should have done even more. You should have done the higher
level. Okay? That would have had תם tam down here and מועד
muad over here. But then we come, bring them together. Okay? דיליף
נגיחה ליתם נגיחה למועד. d'yalif negicha l'tam negicha l'muad. It says יגח
yigach and יגח yigach in both places, so we upgrade the תם.
tam. Once we get to the מועד, muad, ולא ישמרנו, v'lo yishmerenu,
which means you have to do a high level, we're going to
say that applies even to a תם. tam. All right, you get
it. The idea is you have to do a high level of
שמירה. What's רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, which is the complete inverse logic?
רבי יהודה סבר Rabbi Yehuda savar סתם שורים בחזקת שמירה קיימי. stam
shorim bechezkat shmira kaymi. No, no, no. The תורה Torah presumed that
you were watching your ox and nevertheless it says you're going to
pay for a תם. tam. אמר רחמנא תם משלם amar Rachmana tam
meshaleim דבעי שמירה מעולה. d'ba'i shmira meula. So already by a תם,
tam, if it's making you pay, your standard level of watching wasn't
enough. In order to get out of a תם, tam, the תורה
Torah wanted you to do the highest level of watching. Okay? הדר
אמר רחמנא hadar amar Rachmana ולא ישמרנו גבי מועד. v'lo yishmerenu gabei
muad. And then it says by a מועד, muad, ולא
ישמרנו, v'lo yishmerenu, which suggests even more than the highest. How could
you do more than the highest? דהוי שמירה מעולה, d'havi shmira meula,
הוי ריבוי אחר ריבוי. havi ribui achar ribui. It's making a high
demand out, like it's adding something after adding something, increasing after increasing.
ואין ריבוי אחר ריבוי אלא למעט. v'ein ribui achar ribui ella l'ma'et.
Since you were already at the highest level of שמירה by a
תם, tam, and then it said by the מועד muad and you
should have done a שמירה, it's actually coming to say the opposite.
By a תם, tam, as long as you'd done any שמירה would
have been okay.
No, he's like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer then. It means, it means,
I
understand, yeah, you could have, I know. Okay, I get it.
מהי קא כתיב ושמירה מועד? mai ka ketiv v'shmira muad? So therefore
it says that you don't have to do for a מועד, muad,
you don't have to do the high level. Minimum level's okay. וכי
תימא נגיחה ליתם נגיחה למועד? v'chi teima negicha l'tam negicha l'muad? Oh,
so now once we got the מועד muad to be down to
a low level, let's link מועד muad and תם tam and bring
down the תם tam to a low level as well. המעיט רחמנא
ולא ישמרנו. himeit Rachmana v'lo yishmerenu. You did not watch it. דוקא
ולא ישמרנו davka v'lo yishmerenu means you didn't do a minimum watching
of it, of the מועד. muad. וזה ולא לאחר. v'zeh v'lo l'acher.
Only for this and not for another one. Meaning, so only for
the מועד muad is a minimum level acceptable, not for a תם.
tam. Now of course, whatever you do with the פסוק, pasuk, okay,
this is a crazy idea, right? How could it be that you
have less שמירה needed for a מועד muad than for a תם?
tam? So I'm going to tell you what I told you earlier,
which actually fits with the language of the גמרא of סתם שורים
בחזקת שמירה. stam shorim bechezkat shmira.
And what I said is the following, is that רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda fits very well with the idea that a תם tam is
a קנס. knas. If a תם tam is a קנס, knas, it
means that you
never had, there was no good reason for you to pay. Okay?
You weren't at fault. You should have there was no reason to
expect an ox to gore, which by the way fits with a
different read of the phrase of the גמרא, סתם שורים בחזקת שמירה.
stam shorim bechezkat shmira.
It doesn't just mean that most people normally watch their ox. What
it means is an ox could
be presumed to be watched by itself. Oxen don't go out and
gore. Okay? And nevertheless, you have to pay for a תם. tam.
So the reason you're paying is not because you're at fault, you
weren't at fault. It's just arbitrary. We're going to make you pay
for a תם. tam. Okay? Well, if it's arbitrary, okay, then I
can never get out of it. I was anyway, I said, well,
I watched it, I wasn't at fault. You're at fault even when
you didn't watch it. The only way you'd be פטור patur is
if you did the maximum שמירה and then it still happened, then
it's like an act of God. Okay? Then it's not like at
all connected to you. But otherwise, claiming you weren't at fault, you
weren't at fault,
you weren't at fault to begin with and we're still making you
pay. Okay? So a תם tam is arbitrary. It's your animal that
gored, you got to pay half even if you're not to blame.
Okay? A מועד muad you're paying because... Because for normal reasons, because
you were negligent and you were at fault. So once you do
a minimum level of שמירה you're no longer negligent, then you're no
longer then you're no longer going to pay. This is normal and
once you're not negligent you're exempt. This is arbitrary and that you're
always going to pay. Of course the logic is is that how
does how do we go easier on you just because you became
more to blame? And that's why we're going to see the position
we said earlier that רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says
stam- that צד תמות במקומו עומדת. tzad tamut bimkomo omedet. You remember
that idea? So that even when you do a minimum level for
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda this actually makes sense why you want to
say this רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda. Because this is counter-intuitive. When you
do a minimum level it gets you out of the liability of
fault but you should still have the the strict liability of half
payment that you always pay for a תם. tam. The half payment
for תם tam is not based on fault. So that should always
remain even after it becomes a מועד. muad. So you'll get out
of the מועד muad payment which is based on fault but you
won't get out of the תם tam payment. Okay. So let's take
a look about that in the גמרא. Okay. So let's just read
one more- a few more lines. ומה דאיילי ליה לאו? u'mah d'ayeli
lei lav? What do you mean? How can you say ולא ישמרנו
velo yishmerenu means to tell me that you only need to do
a minimum only for a מועד muad is a שמירה פחותה okay.
You need it for a prohibition- it doesn't mean a prohibition, רש"י
Rashi says it means to tell you that you're liable because you
didn't do a
שמירה. No, אם כן נכתב רחמנא ולא ישמור. im kein nechtav rachmana
velo yishmor. Because you didn't do a שמירה you're paying. מאי ולא
ישמרנו? mai velo yishmerenu? You didn't watch it. לזה ולא לאחר. lizeh
velo l'acher. This one and not another. So that's anyway רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir that says only the מועד muad do you get off
of the שמירה פחותה. תניא. tanya. We're talking a ברייתא. Baraita. רבי
אלעזר בן יעקב אומר. Rebbi Elazar ben Yaakov omer. אחד תם ואחד
מועד ששמרו שמירה פחותה פטור. echad tam ve'echad muad she'shamru shmira pechuta
patur. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? So he actually says תם tam and
מועד muad are both down here. That's a fourth position. I don't
have a fourth color. Okay, I guess I have red. רבי אלעזר
בן יעקב. Rebbi Elazar ben Yaakov.
There's a green here.
Okay, I use green already. רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rebbi Elazar ben
Yaakov says תם tam and מועד muad are both down here. Okay,
they both have a minimum שמירה. Okay. מאי
טעמא? mai ta'ama? סבר לה כרבי יהודה דאמר מועד בשמירה פחותה סגי
ליה. savar lah k'Rebbi Yehuda d'amar muad b'shmira pechuta sagi lei. ויליף
נגיחה לתם נגיחה למועד. ve'yalif negicha l'tam negicha l'muad. He holds like
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda that starts like this but then once it
had נגיחה נגיחה negicha negicha the תם tam got pulled down to
the מועד. muad. All right, fine. We have all four possibilities. I
just want to read this next line of צד תמות במקומו עומדת
tzad tamut bimkomo omedet because it's almost necessary to say this within
רבי יהודה's Rebbi Yehuda strange idea. Okay. אמר רב אדא בר אהבה
לא פטר רבי יהודה אלא צד העד שבו. amar Rav Adda bar
Ahava lo patar Rebbi Yehuda ela tzad ha'ad she'bo. When רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda went easy on the מועד muad it was only for
the additional payment of the מועד, muad, the other half, אבל צד
תמות במקומו עומדת. aval tzad tamut bimkomo omedet. The תם tam half
you're always going to pay for. It's the same way this was
an arbitrary payment whatever that's because your ox gored you pay half,
that remains true and that's that strict liability even when we add
the additional fault liability of the מועד. muad.
You'll still pay חצי נזק chatzi nezek like a תם. tam.
If you do a שמירה פחותה for a מועד muad you'll pay
חצי נזק chatzi nezek like a תם. tam. אמר רב מועד ל.
amar Rav muad l-. Okay, you know what, we'll have to stop
here. Okay, so there was one more point the גמרא is going
to make about צד תמות במקומו עומדת tzad tamut bimkomo omedet but
we'll pick up with this tomorrow.